Nicolás Vila

🜎 niicovila | in niicovila | 🏶 niicovila.github.com | 💌 nicolasvila@uchicago.edu | 🖡 +34 692201580

Summary

I am a recently graduated machine learning engineer with a strong technical orientation. My research interests include reinforcement learning, optimal control, and developing AI models that can reason and act. I am passionate about applying deep learning techniques to solve complex problems.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Engineer Intern, Amazon EU

Jun 2023 - Oct 2023 (Barcelona, Spain)

- Part of the Data Engineering team at ATS (Amazon Transportation Services) which handles data pipelines used by a range of different internal teams.
- Developed a data analytics pipeline on AWS to deploy dashboards and create automatic alerts from real-time data stored in an RDS Database.

ML Research Assistant, University of Chicago Law School

Mar 2023 - Oct 2023 (Chicago, IL)

- Worked with OpenAI's API and fine-tuned open source Large Language Model LLaMa-v2 for automatic text generation in the realm of Law.
- Developed an AI system capable of drafting appellate legal briefs, worked with a team of attorneys to define methodologies and strategies.

Data Science Clinic Student, Greenwave

Jan 2023 - Mar 2023 (Chicago, IL)

 Research and implementation of computer vision models deployed on a distributed cluster to predict the mass of kelp from images.

EDUCATION

2020 - 2024 Bachelor's Degree at Universitat Pompeu Fabra

(GPA: 8.8/10.0)

Mathematical Engineering on Data Science

Thesis: Regularized Deep Reinforcement Learning from a Linear Programming Perspective

Honors: Numerical Methods, Machine Learning, Signals & Systems I, Probability, Operating Systems

2022 - 2023 Exchange student at The University of Chicago

(GPA: 3.5/4.0)

Coursework: Time Dependent Data, Introduction to Cryptography, Introduction to Quantum Computing, Data Science Clinic, Entrepreneurship in Technology, Multivariate Statistical Analysis, Introduction to Database Systems.

2023 University of Chicago Booth School of Business

Coursework: Big Data.

2022 Toyota Technological Institute at Chicago (TTIC)

Coursework: Fundamentals of Deep Learning.

PROJECTS

Entropy-Regularized Deep RL with Linear Programming

Link to code

Developed a practical implementation of Q-REPS using deep neural networks (DNNs). Performed a large-scale empirical study using a distributed cluster to understand the impact of various practical design choices. Developed a novel primal-dual policy iteration algorithm and tested it in a tabular setting. (**PyTorch, Gymnasium**)

Hierarchical Deep Learning Model for Time Series Anomaly Detection

Link to demo

Developed and trained a Transformer-LSTM based hierarchical model for anomaly detection, consumption pattern recognition and prediction using daily water consumption time series data recorded from 2019 to 2022. (Pytorch, Streamlit)

VQ-VAE Paper Extension

Link to demo

A modification of the VQ-VAE (Vector-Quantised Variational Auto-Encoder) paper decreasing by a half the reconstruction error.(**PyTorch**)

Analytics WebApp with ML and explainable AI for car price prediction

Link to demo

Developed a WebApp that features data analysis and incorporates a predictive model trained using LightGBM on automobile data. The application also includes a model explainability section to interpret the model's performance.(Scikit-Learn, Streamlit)

Leadership & Activities

Finalist in the 2023 AB Data Challenge

Dec 2024 (Barcelona, Spain)

Our Hierarchical DL model predicted water consumption and detected over 50k anomalies.

Contestant at the 2022 ICPC SWERC

Apr 2022 (Barcelona, Spain)

- Solved several competitive programming problems representing UPF.

Finalist of the "Big Data Challenge" by "CaixaBank"

Mar 2018 (Barcelona, Spain)

 One of the 10 finalists in a nation-wide contest organised by CaixaBank. Participated in the final dataton in Barcelona, Spain.

Skills & Languages

Technical Skills Python, PyTorch, C, C++, Java, JavaScript, Matlab, R, Docker, Git, Linux, SQL, AWS, Spark, Hug-

gingface, Gymnasium

Languages Spanish (Native), English (C1) and Catalan (Native).

Last updated: June 19, 2024